<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Recusants conversion a sermon preached at St. James, before the Prince on the 25. of Februarie. 1608. By Daniell Price Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850424</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850424</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15626</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10056)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15626)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1183:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Recusants conversion a sermon preached at St. James, before the Prince on the 25. of Februarie. 1608. By Daniell Price Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15626:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15626:1"/>
            <p>RECVSANTS CONVERSION: A SERMON PREACHED AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. JAMES, before the PRINCE on the 25. <hi>of Februarie.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <p>BY DANIELL PRICE <hi>Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>At Oxford,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15626:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15626:2"/>
            <head>TO THE ILLVSTRIOVS PRINCE HENRIE, PRINCE OF Great Britaine and DVKE of CORN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WAYL, <hi>the glory of grace in this</hi> life and the grace of glorie in the future.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eligious &amp; moſt Gratious Prince, let me craue pardon for my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, in offring that vnto the eie of the world, which I late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preached in the eare of your Highneſse. The vnde ſerved &amp; vnexpected attention, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer acception of theſe labours, haue drawne this little gift, in repreſentation of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance therein: VVith this, I preſent my ſelfe and ſervice, being ever ready with all my power to doe your Highneſſe the humbleſt duty, thinking my ſelfe happie, when I may performe any thing which may teſtifie my true, zealous, and dutiful affection. Your highneſſe hath already cunning Aholiab, and Bezaleel, ſweet ſinging David, Parable ſpeaking Eccleſiaſtes, Sinne ſmiting Micaiah, Ionas powerfull for Contrition, Peter potent for compunction, Barnabas ſinguler for Conſolation. Theſe all haue dedicated and conſecrated their labours to the building of Gods temple in you: For my owne part I confeſſe I am not able with theſe, to bring taches, or rings, or earings, or bracelets, or iewels of gold, or Onix
<pb facs="tcp:15626:3"/>ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, or Sittim wood, or ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or ſpices, or perfumes, but the little oile which I haue, I deſire to preſent for the light of the Temple. Your Grace is the comforte of the old, the hope of the young, and the ioy of all, <hi>tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad clarum &amp; beneficum ſidus certatim ad volant,</hi> they ſtriue to flocke to your Highneſse as to the comfortable starre of their happineſſe, wiſhes, praiers, preſents, be their offrings. VVith me it is worſe then with many, I haue nothing to preſent, vnleſſe as Eſchines did to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, I ſhould preſent my ſelfe, and ah las in my ſelfe I finde that there is ſuch a diſproportion betweene a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents worthineſse<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and my weakneſse, that even in this, I had beene diſanimated, had I not beene by your gratious favour encouraged. It now remaineth, that in the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt manner I can deviſe, I wholy reſigne my ſelfe, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, labours, endeavours, &amp; courſe of life to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe protection and diſpoſition, craving pardon for my boldneſſe, and ever praying for your Highneſſe bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that you may be truly gratious in this life, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glorious in the life to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe moſt humbly devoted in all ſervice DANIELL PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:15626:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſay. 2.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Come and let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of Iacob.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lord, for many yeeres togither had manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to be the God of <hi>Iſraell</hi> &amp; expected that his people would become the <hi>Iſraell</hi> of God, it proved at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, that <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſins, made them to become <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maels</hi> ſonnes, &amp; of a choſen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration a royall Prieſthood, a peculiar people, a holy nation, they became an vnwiſe and fooliſh generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a diſobedient and rebellious generation, a generation that ſet not their harts aright, &amp; whoſe ſpirit was not confident in their God, diſhonouring Gods Maieſtie, deſpiſing Gods mercy, abuſing his goodnes, abaſing his glory, prophaning the Kings <hi>holyday</hi> the <hi>Saboath</hi> of the Lord, poluting the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> the <hi>Chamber of Preſence</hi> of the Lord, neglecting <hi>his precepts</hi> the <hi>Acts of Parliament</hi> of the Lord, conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning <hi>his holy-ones the Privy Counſell</hi> of the Lord, not regarding him as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who had adopted them his ſonnes, or as a Maſter who had hired them his ſervants, or as a huſband who had eſpouſed them as his wife, or as a Lord who had delivered them as his people, out of the fie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y furnace of the land of Aegypt of the houſe of bondage. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord ſent forth his heavenly heralds the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, with their celeſtiall proclamations, to ſignifie his anger conceiued againſt their ſinnes, and yet his mercie if it were received by ſinners, that ſo he might
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15626:4"/>invi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thoſe that did rebel, incite thoſe that did neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, haſten thoſe that did linger, and recall thoſe that did wander, to ſue out their pardons and to recouer thoſe places that they had loſt in the houſe of his Courts.<note place="margin">Etym. nom. Propheta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Thus ſent hee forth <hi>Eſay</hi> his <hi>health</hi> to heale their ſickneſſe, <hi>Ieremie</hi> his <hi>exaltation</hi> to bring them to humiliation, <hi>Eſekiell his strength</hi> to helpe their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>Daniel his iudgement</hi> to manifeſt his mercie &amp; by theſe 4. as by 4. tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets or by the 4. windes or by the 4. rivers of Paradiſe or by the 4. Evangeliſts he doth ſend out his ſpirituall Purſevants with their celeſtiall proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Our Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> is one of theſe foure who having ſounded a Parle in the former Chapter and having conteſted with this people,<note place="margin">Summa to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius primi capitis.</note> proueth <hi>that they are a ſinfull nation, a people full of iniquity, ſeed of the wicked, corrupt children, their whole head ſicke and their whole hart beauy ſo that from the ſole of the foote to the crowne of the head nothing but wounds and ſores &amp; ſwelling &amp; corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the land waſt, the cities burnt Zion like a beſeedged Citie, the faithful Citie become a harlot, the ſiluer droſse, the wine water, the Princes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious:</hi> and that therfore <hi>the Lord would conſume the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vtterly ouerthrowe them.</hi> Yet not withſtanding all this their miſerie, in this Chapter, hee prophecieth of Gods great mercie, that there ſhalbe a time of the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtauration of the Church, of the erection of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of the election of the Gentiles, the houſe of the Lord ſhalbe prepared vpon the mountaine and the mountaine of the houſe of the Lord ſhalbee prepared on the top of the mountaines &amp; ſhalbe exalted aboue al the hills and the people ſhal reſort thervnto, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15626:4"/>ſhal mutually and reciprocally, excite, and ſolicite, each others with theſe words of my Text. <hi>Come &amp; let vs goe vp to the houſe of the Lord to the mountaine of the God of Jacob.</hi> Which words emblematicallie doe deſcribe <hi>Eccleſia militantis ſymbolum, triumphan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis exercitium</hi> the true ſigne of the Church militant on earth, and the holy exerciſe of the Church trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing in heauen. Wherin if devotion, compunction, conuerſion, aſſention, or religion may moue, let him that hath an eare heare what the ſpirit ſaith vnto the Church, or rather what the Church ſpeaketh with the ſpirit, come and let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord to the houſe of the God of Jacob. If vnitie; amitie, or vnamitie maie moue, if the prophet who was a noble courtier or the people who were worthy Converts, or the place they goe to, to the houſe of God, or the God of that houſe <hi>Deus Iacobi</hi> maie draw attention from you. O then come, &amp; ſee, and heare, &amp; taſt, the gratious goodnes of the Lord in the ſociety of his Saints, with one minde &amp; one mouth inuiting one another with theſe words come and let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord to the houſe of the God of Jacob: <hi>Come</hi> here is the mutuall inuitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let vs, here is the louing coniunction, <hi>Goe vp</hi> here is the ſpiritual aſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>to the mountaine of the Lord.</hi> here is the place for heauenly deuotion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the houſe of the <hi>God of Iacob</hi> here is the Lord of hoſts habitation. <hi>Come and let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord to the houſe of the God of Iacob.</hi> Without anie further deſcant, obſerue with me theſe particulars. 1. a motiue <hi>Come</hi> 2. the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons mutually mouing and moued <hi>let vs.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> the ſubiect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15626:5"/>of the moutie <hi>goe vp.</hi> 4. the place whether they goe <hi>to the mountaine of the Lord. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the geſts of theſe Gentiles progreſſe, and the points in the progreſſe,<note place="margin">1. Obſ. Illir. cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> that J am to point at And firſt let the motiue moue you to attention <hi>Come. Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> noteth that the word in the original ſignifieth, as much as haſten or diſpatch and <hi>Montanus</hi> on the ſame word obſerueth <hi>Hoc verbum studiorum excitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, magis quam corporis metum explicat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In hos c. 6.1</note> That this word ſignifieth not ſo much a motion of the bodie as a deuotion of the minde, and yet ſomtimes maie ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie both, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> on the like place noteth by theſe words. <hi>Venite add<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mum Dei, venite ad doctrinam huius domus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Doctrine.</note> 
               <hi>venite ad obedientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> huius doctrinae.</hi> The word <hi>Come</hi> in this place adminiſtreth this doctrine that it is the dutie of Gods children, not only to bee forward themſelues in godlines but alſo as much as they maie to drawe on others as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Hierome obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. <hi>Non ſunt propria ſalute contenti ſed ſe mutuo prouocant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reaſon. Hier. in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeam 6.1. Reaſon of doct.</note> The reaſon of this doctrine is this everie Chriſtian muſt worke by faith to apprehend his owne ſaluation, and alſo by loue to comprehend as many as he maie, within the compaſſe of the promiſe: Now faith worketh by loue, and mutual loue is ſo eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required as without this faith is dead, hope a vaine preſuming, holyneſſe hypocrifie, zeale, ſurie, loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mother of grace, the daughter of ſanctitie the glaſſe of religion, the marriadge garment &amp; the key of Paradiſe, and ſeeing that faith worketh by loue, what greater loue can there be, of one to a nother then for Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to bring their bretheren from the ſnares of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15626:5"/>Sathan into the glorious libertie of the ſonnes of God,<note place="margin">Grego. Hom. 10. in Ezech.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie in his Homiles vpon Ezethiel</hi> obſerueth this, <hi>Quid eſt quod haec pennata animalia viciſsim alas alteram ad alieram feriunt &amp;c.</hi> What doeth the ioint moouing of theſe Cherubins ſignifie but that all the Saints of God doe by their vertues incite one another to the performance of holy duties?<note place="margin">Aquinas.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> vpon the 12. of Eſay, vrgeth that as ſinners doe incite others, to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by drawing cords of vanitie with the cartropes of iniquitie, howe much more ſhould the Godly ſeeke to draw others to the affection of religious pietie. For ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the wicked crie <hi>Come</hi> &amp; let vs laie wait for blood <hi>Prov.</hi> 1: 11. How much more ſhoulde the godly excite each others, with o come and let vs ſing vnto the Lord. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.1. ſeeing that the wicked crie Come to Bethel and tranſgreſſe, to Gilgal and multiplie tranſgreſſions.<note place="margin">Prov. 1.11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal, 95.1. <hi>Amos,</hi> 4.4. Hoſea, 6.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ. in Chro. Epiph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſ. 78. Orig, lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Gen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſid, de rit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anct, Euſ. l. 3.1. Chro. 12 Hom. 2.</note> to ſaie Come &amp; let vs returne vnto the Lord? <hi>Hoſea.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>This hath beene the practiſe of the godly in all ages being themſelues called and reclaimed &amp; converted to conuert, and to reclaime others. So did the Apoſtles the bleſſed ſeruants of our Lord and Sauiour beeing called from fiſhermen to be fiſhers of men, they conuerted ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nations, as Eccleſiaſtical hiſtories teſtifie a <hi>Peter converting Antiochia,</hi> b <hi>Iohn Aſia,</hi> c <hi>Andrew Scithia,</hi> d <hi>Philip Gallia,</hi> e <hi>Thomas Parthia,</hi> f <hi>Bartholomew Armenia,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Hier. in epiſ. ad Gal Fact Chro Baronius &amp; all.</note> 
               <hi>Simon Zelotes Meſapotamia, and Ioſeph of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea our Britannia.</hi> Yea not only the inſtructions but alſo the actions of verie heathens haue bin potent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to the wiſeſt &amp; worthieſt of the world drawing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the imitation of their vertues. The ſpeech of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15626:6"/>his Tropheys and Victories was the cauſe of <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> affecting and obtaining that renowned glorie as <hi>Suetonius</hi> recordeth:<note place="margin">Sue in Iulio Plut in The miſtocle.</note> And the cauſe of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> glory was the following of <hi>Miltiades</hi> ſteps of dignitie, as <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> teſtifieth. And ſo thoſe many examples, of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> fortitude, <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> wiſdome, <hi>Anthonius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> care of the Common wealth, <hi>Ariſtoteles</hi> learning, <hi>Catoes</hi> ſeueritie, <hi>Scipio</hi> his continencie, <hi>Loelius</hi> amitie, <hi>Fabritius</hi> integritie, <hi>Phillip</hi> of macedon his pollicy, made them to be as preſidents of theſe vertues to al ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ages,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 5 de ciuitate Dei c. 15.16</note> in ſo much that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> proueth that they haue bin honored in al nations, not only bringing other nations in ſubiection to their Countrie, but alſo in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to the imitation of their excellencie by their precepts and counſailes, and inſtructions, and actions. Much more is the power and force, &amp; much more ſhall be the honor of thoſe that lead others, to Godlines, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they that be wiſe ſhal ſhine as the brightnes of the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, &amp; they that turne manie to righteouſnes ſhal ſhine as the ſtarrs for ever more <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3</note> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in <hi>Ezech.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth euerie one to cauſe on another to returne <hi>Ezec.</hi> 18.32.<note place="margin">Exod. 18 3</note> Exhorting one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and prouoking one another, and edifieing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as the Apoſtle counſelleth.<note place="margin">1. The. ſ 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 1. <hi>Theſs.</hi> 5.11. euerie man concluding as the Pſalmiſt loe here am J and the ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and the ſubiect and the people, &amp; the children that thou haſt giuen me. A doctrine ſeruing firſt for this vſe, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couradge al true and faithful Chriſtians to take euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to bring others vnto the Lord,<note place="margin">Vſus</note> and to vſe all meanes for their brethrens ſaluation, but eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe that are in place of eminencie and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15626:6"/>becauſe the actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the leaders are as ſpurs to the followers <hi>&amp;</hi> their <hi>exemplary prouocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible then their mandatory proclamations.</hi> For how did al in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> affect chiualrie becauſe he was a ſouldier, and Poetry in <hi>Augustus</hi> time becauſe he was a Poet &amp; fencing in <hi>Commodus</hi> time becauſe he loued ſencing. How forwards were al in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in the time of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine</hi> becauſe he was a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,<note place="margin">Lact. diuin. inſtit. lib 5.</note> How backward in the time of <hi>Julian</hi> when he fel to Apoſtacie, <hi>Lactantius</hi> could ſaie that to imitate the manners yea the vices of Princes was held an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>The example of the Prince is the greateſt provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to doe good or evill. A Prince is as the higheſt Sphere, the lower Spheres haue their action, motion, imitation from him. There is ſuch a Concatenatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in government that where there is a good king there is alſo a good kingdome, a good Counſel, a good Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and a good Commonwealth, the axiome euer true, <hi>Rex velit honeſta nemo non eadem velit.</hi> If the hart of a Prince bee ſet vpon honeſt things the hartes of al others wil be ſet vpon the ſame things with him. The vertues of priuate men, bee only their owne, of Princes and great men all the worlds, <hi>dicta edicta, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta exempla.</hi> Their actions breed axioms, their words examples. If they once doe that which is prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, their ſchollers will be many. The diſeaſe of the head, is the head of al diſeaſes. O how ought great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be aduiſed then, in their actions, not only for their owne ſake, but for the auaile of others, that by vertue they may breed vertue, that their goodneſſe may not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15626:7"/>only be <hi>immanent</hi> but alſo <hi>tranſient,</hi> eſpecially ſeeing their names, places, offices, powers, and honour bee worth no eſtimation vnleſſe vertuous and not vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, vnleſſe exemplarie to moue and draw and excite others vnto pietie and Chriſtianity, they being the watch men, and rulers, and heads, and ſhepheards of the people as <hi>Homer</hi> calleth <hi>Agamemnon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. Ill 10</note>
            </p>
            <q>— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:</q>
            <p>Which <hi>Caeſar</hi> truly ſhewed himſelf to be,<note place="margin">Polycrat.</note> neuer vſing the word <hi>Ite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Vſe.</note> but the word of my Text, <hi>Venite, Come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly this may ſerue to the reproach of thoſe that come not at all vnto the Lord, who being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held by their riches, or withdrawn by their pleaſures, or detained by their profits, or bewitcht by their ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and liueleſſe cogitations they deferre &amp; procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate their comming vnto the Lord, not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafing to come to ioine with the congregation of his Saints.<note place="margin">Laert. in vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta Diog</note> Againſt whom <hi>Diogenes</hi> ſhall be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who was ſo diligent in comming to <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> that he told him, he ſhould not finde a ſtaffe ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beate him from him, whileſt hee had anie thing to teach him: And <hi>Scipio</hi> ſhal riſe in iudgement againſt them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iuie.</note> who was ſo deuout in daily frequenting the Capitoll to performe diuine offices, that hee was had in great honour among the Romanes for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion. But alas <hi>Epicuriſme, Atheiſme. Paganiſme, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſme, Barowiſme</hi> and <hi>Papiſme,</hi> haue ſo enchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted many amongſt vs, that they will not come vnto our Church, Charme the Charmer neuer ſo wiſely. Eſpecially our malitious enemies the <hi>Edomites,</hi> &amp; <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites,</hi> the Papiſts who by their doctrinal contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15626:7"/>and perſonall maledictions, doe diſgordge the impoſtumes of their poiſonfull ſtomackes againſt our faith, truth, religion, King, and God, &amp; framing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues a religion out of the fragments, and remnants, of the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hereſies, they are become heires appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all thoſe monſters of Sathans kingdome, the <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſts,</hi> and <hi>Maniches,</hi> and <hi>Euſtathians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hull, in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytick A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt, Orm erod in picture, of Pap. &amp; multi a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ij.</note> and <hi>Pellagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Collyridians,</hi> and <hi>Carpocratians:</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onits.</hi> and <hi>Valentinians,</hi> deſpiſing the truth, which was deliuered by <hi>Angels,</hi> preached by <hi>Prophets,</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by <hi>Apostles,</hi> witneſſed by <hi>Martyrs,</hi> ſealed by the bloud of many thouſand <hi>Saints,</hi> and the worldes <hi>Saviour,</hi> and do ſo farre condemne and contemne vs and our religion, as that they thinke it moſt meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if they could aboliſh vs &amp; our ſeruice of God out of the land of the liuing. Such are theſe, ſeed of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> Sonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> workemen of <hi>Babell,</hi> Pyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of <hi>Hell:</hi> ſo much are they incenſed againſt vs, as that they are become blood-thirſty <hi>Crocodiles,</hi> hart-gnawing <hi>Vultures,</hi> dilaniating <hi>Lyons,</hi> poyſonful <hi>Aſpes,</hi> in laying ſnares more ſubtile then <hi>Doeg,</hi> for wicked Counſell worſe then <hi>Achitophell,</hi> for blaſphemous impietie farre aboue <hi>Rabſhakah,</hi> for diueliſh hunting more truculent then <hi>Nimrod</hi> for murther and maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre more ſauadge then <hi>Herod,</hi> for betraying of their God, and King, and religion, and land, and Nation, more deuiliſh then euer any of the tribe of <hi>Iudas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that they had remoued their blindfolded igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ignorant Idolatry, or that they were remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued out of the land: that ſo we might all goe togither, as ſheepe of one ſheephard, ſonnes of one father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritours
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15626:8"/>of one kingdome, Inhabiters of one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and ſo might trauell togither to that eternal Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem where the ſpirit and the bride ſay <hi>Come,</hi> and let him that is a thirſt Come,<note place="margin">Reuel.</note> and let whoſoeuer will, Come and drinke freely of the water of life, that ſo with mutuall minds all of vs might moue each others as they heare doe, Come, and let vs. And ſo let vs Come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the word <hi>Come</hi> to the words <hi>let vs</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons mouing and moued.</p>
            <p>And here firſt behold the greateſt Change,<note place="margin">2. Obſer.</note> muta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, alteration, <hi>metamorphoſis</hi> that euer was: foes receiued as friends, aliants as citizens, enemies as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, the reiected as elected, the Sonnes of the bond woman made free, ſtrangers to the promiſe made heires. The Gentiles who had no couenant in hope, no hope in God no God in the worlde, are now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, accepted, approued. On the other ſide behold with terror and trembling, the right Oliue tree made a wilde branch, the Citizens made aliants, the heires made ſtrangers, <hi>Iacob</hi> a ſupplanter, ſupplanted, <hi>Eſau</hi> reiected, receiued, <hi>Iſraell,</hi> made <hi>Iſmaell, Iſmael</hi> made <hi>Iſraell</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to whom appertained the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, and the glory, and the couenant, and the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of law, and the ſeruice of God, and the promiſe, are now become a froward generation.<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> The Iews per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, and the Gentiles co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted. The doctrine that hence I gather, is this, they that turne from God, he wil turne from them, and they that turne to the Lord, he will turne to them.<note place="margin">Reaſon. 1. Sam. 2.13</note> The reaſon and proofe of this doctrine, is that of God himſelfe. <hi>Jn Sam. They that honour me I will honour them, and they that deſpiſe me
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15626:8"/>I will deſpiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Though the <hi>Jewes</hi> were the people, whoſe fathers he had loued, whoſe ſeed he had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, whom he brought out of the lande of Aegypt, for whom he ſhewed ſo many miracles, and to whom he manifeſted ſo many mercies, a people as deere to him as the apple of his eie, as nere as the ſignet on his right hand, yet, if they forſake him they ſhall be fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, famiſhed, ſcattered, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed, &amp; vtterly reiected, and on the other ſide, though the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple odious in the ſight of God and men, an adulterous and Idolatrous generation, yea though their ſinnes were as red as ſcarlet, he can make them as white as ſnow, though as red as crimſon, if they will turne, hee can make them as white as wool: A ſtrange mutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, an vnheard of <hi>Metamorphoſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall I tel you of <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſo ſtrong, that proued ſo weake, of <hi>Salomon</hi> ſo wiſe, that proved ſo fooliſh, of <hi>Peter</hi> a Paſtor, that prove an impoſtor, of <hi>Iudas</hi> a preacher, that proued a traitor, of <hi>Paule</hi> a perſecutor, that proued a preacher: what is al this to this? The <hi>Iewes</hi> that were receiued are reiected, &amp; the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that were reiected, are receiued.</p>
            <p>Shall I tell you? that al the <hi>world</hi> was deſtroied, &amp; a little <hi>arke</hi> deliuered, that al <hi>Sodome</hi> was burned, and little <hi>Soar</hi> defended, that all <hi>Aegypt</hi> was plagued, &amp; little <hi>Goſhen</hi> preſerved: behold theſe with trembling, and adde vnto theſe; this, that the Iewes that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, are reiected, and the Gentiles that were reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, are received.</p>
            <p>Shall I in one word, tel you of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumption, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, ſubverſion, deſolation of the worthieſt ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15626:9"/>and Piles, that ever the ſunne lookt vpon: how <hi>Noe</hi> that was ful of people, and <hi>Babilon</hi> that ſate as a Queene, &amp; <hi>Iericho</hi> that was the citty of Palme trees, and <hi>Tirus</hi> rich with the ſeed of <hi>Nilus,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the ioie of the whole earth, were overthrowne, and all vtterly conſumed. Yet none of theſe are Paralel to this <hi>Catacliſme,</hi> and Inundation of deſolation, that the <hi>Iewes,</hi> the firſt, and beſt, and one, &amp; only beloved people, who had <hi>Abraham</hi> for their father, <hi>Iſraell</hi> for their name, <hi>Moſes</hi> their Prophet, <hi>Aaron</hi> their Prieſt, <hi>Manna</hi> their meat, <hi>Canaan</hi> their Countrie, <hi>Kings</hi> their Captiues, <hi>David</hi> their king, yea <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe their kinſman, and yet theſe Jewes reiected, and Gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiles received.<note place="margin">Vſus.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O conſider this all yee that forget God, howle yee Firre trees that theſe Caedars haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the <hi>Oliue</hi> tree hath loſt her fatneſſe, the <hi>Vine</hi> tree her ſweetneſſe, the <hi>Cedar</hi> her faireneſſe, the <hi>Figge</hi> tree her fruitfulneſſe. O what then remaineth for the brambles and briers, thornes, and thiſtles, but the fire of wrath, and the wrath of fury! O did the world, and the pompe, &amp; the glory thereof conſider this, did thoſe places that now in ioie enioy the pleaſures of the worlde duly regarde this. Did <hi>Venice</hi> ſo bleſſed with riches, <hi>Bononia</hi> with fruits, <hi>Naples</hi> with Nobility, <hi>Millaine</hi> with beautie <hi>Ravenna</hi> ſo honoured for antiquity,<note place="margin">Forraine Countries.</note> or <hi>Florence</hi> for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, did theſe I ſay in the height of their pride, caſt downe their eies vpon the duſt and aſhes and rubble of the worlds more ancient monuments, they would now,<note place="margin">Our owne Land.</note> euen now, in the daies of their peace, thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the time of their viſitation. Did our owne land en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15626:9"/>as gloriouſly, as graciouſly with the bleſſings of peace &amp; plenty, &amp; proſperity as euer <hi>Caanan</hi> was. Did our Land meditate vpon this, it would not ſo far put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her the day of deſolation.<note place="margin">The Citie London.</note> Did the <hi>Citty</hi> prowd of her wals and bulwarks, puft vp in the wealthineſſe of her inhabitants, glorying in the goodlineſſe of her building, vanting her ſelfe to be the mother citty of the land, the Metropolis of the Country, the ſeate of the kingdome, and the Chamber of the King, did this Citty remember this, then her graues would not bee ſo ful, her houſes often ſo empty, her howlings ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, her plagues ſo mighty. Yea to come neerer:<note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iames</note> Did this <hi>Court</hi> wherein I ſpeake, and you the ſtarres of this Zodiake conſider this, it would ſerue to let you blood in the ſwelling vaines of pride, to launce the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtumes of greedy deſires, to purge your ambitious, malitious, voluptuous thoughts, to cure wantonnes, &amp; to curbe the leſt thought of wickedneſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make particular vſe of this doctrin, that ſeeing the Iewes haue fallen, they take heede to that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of <hi>S. Paule,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.12.</note> Let him that ſtandeth take heed leſt he fal. Be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, flatter not thy ſelfe, equivocate not with thy ſoul, though thou ſeeme to bee the deare childe of God, preſume not there vpon, thou maieſt fal, thou art not more ſober then <hi>Noah,</hi> more ſtrong then <hi>Sampſon,</hi> more wiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Salomon,</hi> more chaſt then <hi>David,</hi> more ſecure then <hi>Peter. Cecidere duces,</hi> the Columnes, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Pillers, Piramides haue fallen <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſtrong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue fallen, yea <hi>Iſraell</hi> the very firſt, and beſt, &amp; chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt of Gods people haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their ſtrength hath bin
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15626:10"/>weakned, their beauty blemiſhed, their bloſſoms bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, their honour obſcured, their glory ecclipſed, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue fallen, the beſt of men, more glorious then the beſt of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Patriarchs</hi> haue fallen, <hi>Prophets</hi> haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, <hi>Apoſtles</hi> haue fallen, <hi>Starres</hi> haue fallen, <hi>Angels</hi> haue fallen.</p>
            <p>A ſecond leſſon that we learne in theſe <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 da. 2 dae.</note> is their vnity, and mutual ſociety in their conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting one another: They were not deuided in their wils, not ſeparated in their actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, not diſioind in their affections, but in a heauenly harmony they all ioine togither, mutually inciting, <hi>Come and let vs.</hi> The one and only God and father of vs al, who is God for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, bleſſed world without end, he, in the riches of his wiſdome, &amp; knowledge, hath appointed, that not only the world in things natural, but that his Church alſo in things ſpiritual, ſhould begin, encreaſe, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle.</note> and be perpetuated by vnity. The <hi>Naturalist</hi> looking through the windowes of Nature beheld the one &amp; found <hi>Vnity</hi> to be the apeaſement of al Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, of contrary Elements in the worlde, of contrarie humors in the body, of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the minde, of contrary factions in the Common wealth: and in things ſpiritual, it is ſo heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, as that it is truly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the bond of the <hi>Patriarkes,</hi> the Chariot of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> the refuge of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of <hi>Confeſſours,</hi> and the ſalue of the <hi>Saints.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God himſelfe hath made his faithful people to be al as one, his<note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 6.8.</note> Church he hath made one. He hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them<note n="b" place="margin">Mat 25.34</note> one kingdome, and<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 17 21</note> one wil,<note n="d" place="margin">Ier 32.29</note> one hart, &amp; one way,<note n="e" place="margin">Eze. 1.16.</note> one minde and one ſpirit. So like in loue as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15626:10"/>that with the<note n="f" place="margin">Eſec. 1 16.</note> 
               <hi>Cherubins</hi> in <hi>Ezechiels</hi> viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſeem to haue but one face. So louing in qualitie and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that with al<note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 20.1</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> they are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as one man, ſo conſtant in faith and affection as that they<note n="h" place="margin">Acts 2 46.</note> continue with one accord in the <hi>Temple.</hi> So did theſe Conuerts, they conioine themſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as the true members of Chriſtes bodie, one thought, one wiſh, one deſire, one hart, one tongue, with al which they ioine, <hi>Come and let vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the doctrine which hence ariſeth is this,<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> that it is a ſure ſigne of Chriſtianitie in the Children of God to be at one in the vnitie of the ſpirit. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the doctrin is, that ſeeing there is but one God, one Father, one Redeemer, one Comforter, one milk of the word, one food of the Sacraments,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> ſeeing there is but one faith, one Lord, one baptiſme, ſeeing we all inhabite one vale of miſerie, and valley of teares, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we all fight againſt one enemie, the old ſerpent, ſeeing we al run for one goale, all wreſtle for one gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, al ſtriue for one crowne, al partake in one bodie, and one ſpirit, we might al be one in the Lord Ieſus. And ſo might enioie the bleſſing of vnitie, and amitie and vnanimitie, more pleſant then the pools of <hi>Heſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> more glorious then the Towers of <hi>Lebano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> more redolent then the oile of <hi>Aaron,</hi> more fructifiing, then the deawe of <hi>Hermon,</hi> That ſo we maie be al knit to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether without anie diſiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ction, that whether we bee ſupplicants to the throne of grace, wee maie al of vs come togither, as ioint petitioners, or whether we be the ſingers of thankſgiuing in the houſe of the Lord, we maie al ſing in the harmonie of the ſpirit, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15626:11"/>we be as the company of an army to ſtand in the gap to entreat for Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditions of peace, we may all cry togither, Spare vs good Lord, ſpare thy people, &amp; bee not angrie with thine inheritance: ſo al of vs, being as ſo many <hi>beames,</hi> iſſuing from the <hi>Sun</hi> of righteouſnes, all as <hi>brookes</hi> comming, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>fountaine</hi> of goodnes, al of vs as <hi>nerues</hi> proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>head</hi> of wiſdom, al of vs as <hi>arteries</hi> ſpringing from the <hi>hart</hi> of loue, all of vs as <hi>veines</hi> deriued from the <hi>liver</hi> of life, al of vs as <hi>lines</hi> drawne from the <hi>center</hi> of grace: Al of vs going one way through truth vnto life, through light vnto truth, through loue vnto light, hauing one hope, one faith, and grace of God, in Chriſt Jeſus, the one &amp; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meanes of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>The vſe hereof is to exhort al the Saints,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, to an vniformity in Chriſtianity, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion thereof, that ſo there may be no diuiſion in the body, for ſeeing a body, a houſe, a kingdome cannot ſtand if once deuided, Alas how ſhal the Church of Chriſt, the body of Chriſt, the houſhold of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, the kingdome of heauen vpon earth ſtand if there be ſo manie Sizers and Conciſers, &amp; Cutters &amp; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of her members?<note place="margin">Liuie</note> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> in that ciuil or rather vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuil diſcord betweene <hi>Craſſus,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> had almoſt loſt (by this threefold diſcorde) the three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord of their concorde, and many other Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealths haue been much waſted and impaired by the monſter diſſention.<note place="margin">Tacitus in vita Agrico lae.</note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> in the life of <hi>Agricola</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing the figure, faſhion, complexion, chiualrie and reſolution of the <hi>Britaines</hi> in that time, obſerueth this alſo, that they were then drawne into pety partialities
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15626:11"/>and factions,<note place="margin">Britan, gens vali diſſima. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</note> and the greateſt helpe that the <hi>Romanes</hi> had <hi>adverſus validiſsimas gentes</hi> as he calleth our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was that they had no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel togither, but each citty fought againſt their neighbours, <hi>Et ita dum ſinguli pugnant vniverſi vincu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur,</hi> whileſt one by one fighteth, al are ſubdued. The <hi>Romanes</hi> are againe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring our land, they expect an aduantageous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, by our home-bred factions, and ſchiſmes, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions. But Lord let it neuer come to paſſe, let our Common-wealth and Church be as <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at vnitie, ſafe as <hi>Mount Syon</hi> that ſhal neuer be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued. Let thy Church here be for euer the houſe of peace! O let not her Peace-makers be her Peacebrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, let not her fathers be foſter-fathers of diſſention, but let Patrones be patternes of vnity, let her Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents be the preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of vnity, her Antients beare the ſtandards of vnity, let her be begirt with the wals of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, let her and her ſeruants, &amp; her ſonnes be guided by thee O God, the God of vnity, till the comming of thy Sonne Chriſt Ieſus to iudgment!</p>
            <p>J knowe J ſpeak to an intelligent and ingenious auditorie, J need not expatiat in this of the profit, ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſure, bleſſing, faelicitie of vnitie. You al know that ſhe is the greateſt gift of God, cheifeſt ioy of Angels, hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſt happines of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fearfulleſt terror of diuils, holieſt harmonie of Saints, heauenlyeſt Antheme of Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Cherubins, The <hi>Empreſſe</hi> of the world, whoſe <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie Counſel</hi> be the <hi>vertues,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ladies of honor</hi> bee the <hi>Muſes,</hi> whoſe <hi>neareſt attendants</hi> bee the <hi>Graces,</hi> whoſe <hi>Gard</hi> be <hi>the Angels,</hi> whoſe <hi>Court</hi> is <hi>proſperitie,</hi> whoſe <hi>state</hi> is <hi>felicitie,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſtatuts veritie,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15626:12"/>
               <hi>continuance eternitie, David</hi> his <hi>Ecce,</hi> as the roial vſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of this <hi>Empreſse</hi> bids you behold how good &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and happy, and holy, and heauenlie a thing it is to dwel together in vnity. Hold it, and behold it, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine her, &amp; retaine her, that you maie al ſaie as theſe converts <hi>Come &amp; let vs goe vp.</hi> And ſo J end this point and follow them in their going vp. <hi>Come and let vs goe vp</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The life of a Chriſtian is not the life of ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">2 Obſ.</note> not a profeſſing life, but a practiſing, not a talking life, but a walking, they muſt not only <hi>Come</hi> together but <hi>goe</hi> together, they muſt walke, &amp; goe, &amp; clime, &amp; goe vp.<note place="margin">Goe repent goe vp, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance. 1. Repent.</note> This ditty their dutie, <hi>Come and let vs goe vp.</hi> Jn the word <hi>go</hi> we may note their <hi>repentance;</hi> in their <hi>going vp</hi> their <hi>perſeuerance.</hi> For the firſt they had lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g layen vpon the lees of vngodlines vnſtird, vnmoued, they ſat in the ſeat of the ſcornful, or if they ſtood vp, they ſtood but in the waie of ſinners, or if they walkt they walked but in the counſell of the wicked, <hi>greſsus digreſſus;</hi> but now they take a newe iourney in hand, they chuſe new liuing waies; they goe, <hi>egreſſus regreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> they goe, &amp; goe out, and goe on, and goe vp and turne from the waie of their wickednes and from the wickednes of their waies.<note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> The <hi>doctrine</hi> gathered from the word <hi>goe</hi> is this, that it is a certaine ſigne of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in a penitent ſinner, vpon the firſt knowledge &amp; acknowledgment of his ſinnes, to goe to the throne of grace.<note place="margin">Auſtin. Reaſon.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> giueth the reaſon of this doctrine, Man by his going from God is deformed and poluted and altogether void of al ſpiritual bleſſings, and by his returne and going back to God he obtaineth al thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15626:12"/>bleſſings he formerlie loſt. <hi>Excedendo frigeſcit, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo ferveſcit, Recedendo tenebreſcit, revertendo cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcit,</hi> &amp; therfore theſe conuerts reſolue here as thoſe did of whom <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Austin</hi> ſpeaketh.<note place="margin">In 70. Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Conferamus nos ad te &amp; bene erit nobis de nobis, malum eſt nobis de nobis, &amp; quia commiſimus malum, dimiſiſti nos nobis.</hi> The ſtate of Chriſtians in their conuerſion is vndoubtedly moſt heauenlie, that though Sathan hath aſſaulted them and ſinne hath wounded them, and the world tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and the fleſh betraied them, and temptation entrapped the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet al theſe enimies remoue their bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeedg when the ſoule is deſirous to turne to his God. O how happie is the Chriſtian then when he hath the father calling, the ſonne mouing, the holy ſpirit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading, the word directing, the rewarde inuiting, Saints conuerſing, Angels reioicing, and he himſelfe ſinging that ſweet &amp; holy Hymne <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c dimittis,</hi> Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace from the wicked waies of the world, the fleſh, the deuil, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the companie of al infernall complices, loe J come, J walke, J goe, J runne, J clime, J goe vp to the houſe of the Lord, J repent my ſinns paſt. <hi>video meliora pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> J follow hard to the marke for the high price of my ſaluation! Thus when they returne and for ſinnes ſake leaue ſin, and leauing ſins, repent of ſins, though the lees thereof remaine in them, &amp; if for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake, they labour for righteouſnes, though an eſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial righteouſnes be not inherent in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though they do not al the good they loue, but in loue, deſire to doe it, though they leaue not al the ſinnes they hate, but in hatred labour to reſiſt them, by this returning the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15626:13"/>good we doe is accepted, the good we deſire to doe is imputed, the euil we leaue is diſcharged, the euill wee deſire to leaue, ſhal not be imputed. But alas, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny put from them the thought of repentance? When notwithſtanding that they haue their conſcience ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing them, their ſins oppreſſing them, Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Gods ſpirit warning them, Gods mercie exciting them, And yet alas yet, they are ſo lulled in ſecuritie, as that they thinke not of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne before the Lord quite turne them of.<note place="margin">Strabo in Geog. l. 13,</note> Theſe bee like thoſe of whom <hi>Strabo</hi> writeth in his Geographie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they deferre til it be to late, like to <hi>Hanniball</hi> in ſurpriſing <hi>Rome, Quando potui non habui voluntatem, &amp; quando volui non habui poteſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> They haue <hi>vocem corvinam,</hi> to cry <hi>Cras,</hi> to procraſtinate their returne, but haue not <hi>vocem columbina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mox mox.</hi> They remember not that God hath left but 2 <hi>Tenſes</hi> to man <hi>praeſens &amp; prateritum,</hi> and hath taken the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture into his owne hands, to diſpoſe therof himſelfe: and if they haue beene deceiued of the time paſt, and are deceiued of the time preſent, howe much more may they be of the time future.</p>
            <p>The Saints and ſeruants of God, are carefull vpon the firſt knowledge of their ſins, and errors to returne vnto the Lord. So did<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> from Gentiliſme, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the Jewes,<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> from Iudaiſme, in denying his Maſter,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Sam. 12.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> from his adultery,<note n="d" place="margin">Eccl, 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Salomon</hi> from his Jdolatry,<note n="e" place="margin">2. Chro, 32.26.</note> 
               <hi>Heſekias</hi> the father,<note n="f" place="margin">2, Chro. 33, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Manaſſes</hi> his ſon.<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 8.37.</note> The <hi>Ennuch,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Act. 10, 1.</note> 
               <hi>Cornelius,</hi> the<note n="i" place="margin">Iud. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ioan. 3 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ninivits,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iud. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>Bethulians,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Act, 8, 12,</note> 
               <hi>Samaritanes,</hi> n <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite more.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15626:13"/>
            <p>The vſe of this doctrine is that we confeſſe that we haue al gon aſtraie and done wickedly, euerie one of vs hath wandered out of the waie, and therfore that wee ſeek to the throne of grace there to ſeek this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, this eſpecial gift of God, this ioie of Angels, this ſalue of ſinnes, this hauen of ſinners, denied to An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels, and therfore they became deuils, denied to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and therfore they remaine damned, and only a gift beſtowed on the ſonnes of God. O howe oft hath repentance and conuerſion beene preached, and yet how little hath it beene affected! Jt hath beene prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by <hi>Naoh</hi> to the old world, by <hi>Lott</hi> to <hi>Sodome,</hi> by <hi>Moyſes</hi> to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> by the <hi>Prophets</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to Chriſt, by Chriſt before the Apoſtles, and by many thouſands of the Saints and ſeruants of God ſince in many places, and how often it hath bin prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in this place and to this preſence, the very wood and ſtones, and ſeats, and ſencleſſe creatures ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bear witneſſe. O it wilbe to late to returne <hi>Corpus cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſa,</hi> when the ſentence of condemnation is come from the Kings bench. Come therfore let vs worſhip and fal downe and kneele before the Lord our maker, for hee is the Lord our God, and we are the people of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to daie if ye wil heare his voice harden not your harts, and now euen now while it is time and daie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to returne vnto the Lorde: whatſoeuer thou art that haſt ſtraied from the Lord by pride, returne by the holy waie of humilitie, or by hard harted cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, returne by the bleſſed waie of mercy, or if by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, returne by charitie, or if by couetouſnes, returne by liberalitie, or if by drunckennes, returne by ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15626:14"/>or if by filthineſſe, returne by chaſtitie. In a worde J end this point with the words of our prophet in the 5. verſe of this chapter. O houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> come yee &amp; let vs walke in the light of the Lord!<note place="margin">Eſay. 2.5.</note> And ſo J come to ſtep a ſtep higher from the goeing to their going vp, <hi>Come and let vs goe vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They goe, and walke, and clime, and goe vp. They continue,<note place="margin">2. Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance Goe vp.</note> they perſeuere, with <hi>Hanniballs</hi> ſouldiers they proceed forwards in their iourney, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the rough rocks, and craggy clefts of the Alpes. God cannot abide haulting in his ſeruice, delaying in religion, loitering in profeſſion, limmits in Chriſtian proceſſion, he cannot but diſtaſt any ſnaile-like with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, anie <hi>peece</hi>-like recoilling, any <hi>Hypocriticall</hi> faining, anie weariſome fainting, anie <hi>Dial-like</hi> ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, anie <hi>poole-like</hi> ſtanding, anie <hi>Ephraimite</hi> ſtarting, anie <hi>fooliſh virgin</hi> neglecting, anie <hi>drowſey Apoſtle</hi> ſleeping. The profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a Chriſtian muſt not be like to <hi>Fabia</hi> in <hi>Quintilian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Quint.</note> which for, 30. yeares to gether would not confeſſe ſhe was a yeare elder, or like to the ſunne in <hi>Ioſhuaes</hi> time that ſtood ſtill, or rather the ſunne in <hi>Heſekiah</hi> his time, which went backward, or like to that Mounke who in his quotidian deuotions,<note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Thom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moore.</note> was wont to ſaie the 1 daie <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> the 2 <hi>&amp; filio,</hi> the thirde <hi>&amp; ſpiritui ſancto</hi> and in the ende it was <hi>ſicut erat in principio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuc. in dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. Eraſ in chuy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ds. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pot.</note> dubling ouer his oriſons, or like to <hi>Mandrabulus</hi> in <hi>Lucian,</hi> who the firſt yeare offred a ſheep of gold, the ſecond a ſheep of ſiluer, &amp; the third a ſheep of braſſe; or in a word like to the picture in the Poet, <hi>Definit in piſcem, mulier formoſa ſuperné.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there be who make good entrance but weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15626:14"/>they runn wel at the firſt but they either ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or retire, they begin in the ſpirit &amp; end in the fleſh, the bloſſomes be faire, but when their fruit ſhould be ripe it is rotten, their beginning is good &amp; laudable, but the end is lewd and damnable. The Lorde hateth theſe, and therfore as the eſpecial thing hee requireth in a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to be faithful, ſo the moſt eſpecial thing in the faithful is to bee perfect, euen to be faithful to the death.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine that I hence gather from the words <hi>goe vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note> is this, that the Chriſtian that hath entred into pathes of righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Reaſon.</note> muſt reſolue to walke there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in al the daies of his life. The reaſon of this doctrine is the poſition of Chriſt himſelfe, he that putteth his hand to the plow &amp; draweth it backe, is vnfit for the kingdome of heauen. A Chriſtian therefore muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that as God is α, and ω, ſo he wil haue his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to run from α, to ω, from the beginning to the ending in the conſtant profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the faith: they muſt remember they that were marked to be preſerued in Jeruſalem, they were marked with the Character <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is the laſt of al the Hebrew letters, teaching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they muſt run their race euen to the laſt. Their profeſſion muſt be <hi>Sacramentum militare,</hi> to hold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til death, like to the couenant in our Liturgy of matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, to be kept til death vs depart, like to that in the Poet of <hi>Megara</hi> to her <hi>Hercules:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Seneca.</note>Non vincet fidem vis vlla noſtram,</l>
               <l>Moriar Alcide tua—</l>
            </q>
            <p>They muſt with the<note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 3.4.</note> Spouſe in the Canticles, take hold and not leaue the hold. With<note n="b" place="margin">Io. 20 21.</note> 
               <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15626:15"/>ſtand, and wait, and ſtay at the ſepulchre, they muſt with the<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 15.22</note> woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> crie &amp; continue in cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; calling,<note n="e" place="margin">Heb 12.4</note>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Phil. 4.1.</note> They muſt continue in the Lord, they muſt be ſtedfaſt, and vnmoueable, alwaies abounding in the worke of the Lord.<note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 126.6.</note> They muſt goe, and go on, yea they muſt goe, and go vp with theſe Iſraelites:</p>
            <q>Non eſt ad astra mollis è terris via,</q>
            <p>They muſt go on, go vp, clime and aſcend, if they will be trulie vpright, they muſt go right vp to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of <hi>Iacob.</hi> The vſe herof is to exhort thoſe that are matriculated in the book of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> that they proue proficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in his Schoole, that they may walke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrength to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, from faith to faith, from vertue to vertue, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace to grace,<note place="margin">Pſ. 84. Rom 1.17 2. Cor. 3: 18</note> and ſo maie at length paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glorie to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. That ſo there be no euil, or vnfaithful hart in vs at any time to fal from the liuing God, not ſtarting aſide as <hi>Ephraim,</hi> not backſliding with <hi>Demis,</hi> not gaineſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Ecebolius,</hi> not repugning with <hi>Iulian,</hi> not turning from the truth with <hi>Phygellus,</hi> and <hi>Hermoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> not making ſhipwracke of a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience with <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> but that for euer, and euer wee conſecrate our bodies to his name, our eares to heare his word, our tongue to ſound his praiſes, our hands to be lifted vp,<note place="margin">4 obſeru.</note> our cheekes to be bedewed, our knees to be bowed, &amp; our feet to aproach his Courts: and ſo I come to the place whether they goe, to the mountaine of the Lord, to the houſe of the God of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> The Church of God in Scripture is compared to manie &amp; ſeueral things,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.10 Elek. 17.6</note> for her louelines to a a <hi>Doue,</hi> for her fruitfulnes to a b <hi>Vine,</hi> for her holyneſſeto a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15626:15"/>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pet. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Priecthood</hi> for her royalneſſe to a<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 45.10</note> 
               <hi>Queene,</hi> for her brightneſſe to the<note n="e" place="margin">Cant. 6.9</note> 
               <hi>Morning,</hi> for her faireneſſe faire as the faireſt of<note n="f" place="margin">Cant. 5.9</note> woeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and here for her ſafeneſſe to mount Syon: not for her viſiblenes, as the Papiſts out of this, &amp; other places affirme, but for her ſtedfaſtnes and ſafeneſſe ſhee is as Mount <hi>Syon,</hi> that ſtandeth faſt fore ermore. For viſibility we hold as it hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten anſwered them, that it is an <hi>externall</hi> ornament, no <hi>neceſſary argument</hi> of Chriſts Church, wee know that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſten</hi> to be true, that the Church is wel compared to the Moone,<note place="margin">In Pſal, 10.</note> for as the Moone receiueth the light from the Sunne, ſo doth the true Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue her light from Jeſus Chriſt the Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. And as the Moone ſo the Church is ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>etimes in the full, &amp; ſhineth in ful brightneſſe, as in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, and diuers hundred yeares after. Some times ſhe is in the waine and ecclipſed, as for manie hundred yeares laſt paſt, it hath beene, in which that Apoſtaſie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith is come, which <hi>S. Paule</hi> by the ſpirit of God foreſhewed. That there ſhould come a departing and the man of ſin ſhould be diſcloſed, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne of perdition. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3. and more plainlie, the ſpirit ſpeaketh euidentlie, that in the latter times ſome ſhal depart from the faith, and ſhal giue heede vnto ſpirits of errour, and doctrine of deuils, which ſpeake lies through hipocriſie, and haue their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences burnt with a hot iron. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. For the viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the Church the argument would as well befit <hi>Bethel</hi> where <hi>Ieroboam</hi> his calues had more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>courſe then the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and might iuſtifie the <hi>Epheſians</hi> clamour, Great is <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:15626:16"/>whom al the world worſhippeth, and is as availeable to proue the <hi>Arrians</hi> to be of the Church,<note place="margin">Naziane.</note> who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured their Church by multitude, not quality; and the <hi>Turke</hi> maie in this conteſt with the Pope, his Church being as apparant in ſhew, as ceremonious for rites, as ſuperſtitious in deuotion, as glorious in Temples, as ancient almoſt for ſucceſſion. Our aduerſaries in this reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber not how in the ſacred ſtories, the Church is hieroglyphically depainted, by <hi>Noahs</hi> arke, by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams progeny, Iobs family, Eliahs complaint, Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadne ſors furnace, the Apoſtles latent,</hi> the <hi>Christians Couchant.</hi> That the Church is like a<note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Lylie</hi> among the Thornes, like a Lylie of the vallies. Like a<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Lodge</hi> in a garden of Cucumers. Like a<note n="c" place="margin">Cant. 2.14</note> 
               <hi>Doue</hi> in the holes of the rockes, and in the ſecret places of the ſtaires,<note n="d" place="margin">Rev. 12.6.</note> like a woman flying into the deſert,<note n="e" place="margin">Eze. 16.5.</note> yea caſt out into the open field, to the contempt of her perſon. Thus hath ſhee bin ſeene and ſkorned, acknowledged, but dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, viſible, but miſerable. Where now is the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent pompe, and glorie, and ſpecioſitie, &amp; eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and perſpicuitie of this Church? I follow theſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible <hi>heretickes</hi> no farther about their viſibility. The Church is here named by the name of a <hi>mountaine,</hi> That God, who among al the <hi>fowles</hi> choſe the <hi>Doue,</hi> among al the <hi>flowers</hi> the <hi>Lylie,</hi> among al <hi>trees</hi> the <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar,</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g al <hi>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Iudaea,</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g al <hi>daies</hi> the <hi>Saboath,</hi> among al <hi>turrets,</hi> the <hi>tower</hi> of <hi>David</hi> among al <hi>Cities Ieruſalem,</hi> among al other <hi>mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines</hi> hath choſen <hi>Syon</hi> for himſelfe. It is not <hi>Babilon</hi> that burnt mountaine. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.25. nor <hi>Horeb</hi> that ſmoaking mountaine <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.18. nor <hi>Eball</hi> that curſing mountaine <hi>Deut</hi> 27.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15626:16"/>nor <hi>Synai</hi> that trembling mountaine <hi>Deut</hi> 4.1. where there was fire to the mideſt of heauen, and darkneſſe, and miſts, and cloudes, and thundring, and lightning, the Trumpet ſounding, and the earth quaking. But it is that prepared mountaine. <hi>Mich.</hi> 4.1. it is that high mountaine <hi>Eſec.</hi> 20.40. It is that holy mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.6. Jt is the mountaine of his name. <hi>Eſay</hi> 18.7 it is the mountaine of his Temple<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Mich.</hi> 3.12. the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his teſtament. <hi>Eſay</hi> 14.13. the mountaine of the houſe of the Lord. <hi>Mons ſupra montes, mons in ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tice montium.</hi> Some take theſe words to be ſpoken of the general Church, ſome of the particular Temple. Some that the Prophet here alludeth by the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to the general, <hi>Sion</hi> was the place where he apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Temple to bee built, this therfore is called the mountaine of his houſe. So that the meaning of the words is this, that they that had beene recuſants from the Church, aliants from the Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> ſhould at the lenght be written in Gods book, incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into Chriſtes bodie, cloathed with Chriſtes righteouſneſſe, admitted to bee ſchollers in Chriſtes Church,<note place="margin">Eſay. 18.7.</note> and receaued to bee inheritours of Chriſtes Kingdome: and as this our Prophet ſpeaketh in his 18. Chap. verſ. 7. At that time a preſent ſhalbee brought vnto the Lord of hoſtes, (a people that is ſcattered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and ſpoiled, and of a terrible people from their beginning hetherto, a nation euen by little and little troaden vnder foot, whoſe Land the riuers haue ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) to the place of the Lord of hoſts to the mount <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Theſe bee the people, theſe the preſent, theſe bee they that come, that goe, that goe on, that goe vp to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15626:17"/>the mountaine of the Lord to the houſe of the god of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The doctrine that J gather from this place is this, that euerie one haue an eſpecial regard and care to knowe whether he be a true member of the Church,<note place="margin">Doct</note> whether he be truly one of the ſocietie of al Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſouls. The reaſon of this doctrine is this they that bee not of this Church they cannot aſſure themſelues of any true ioie,<note place="margin">Reaſon</note> anie true peace, anie true comfort in this life or in that to come. J might proue this by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, but J know not howe J maie be diſpenced with in this congregation for prolixitie of ſpeech and therfore wil drawe vnto an end.<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.1.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 15. Pſalme aſketh this queſtion who be the true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, Lord who ſhal dwel in thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, or who ſhal reſt vpon thy holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine? J referre you to the anſwere, viewe it, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it, read it, then remember. The trueſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that we haue to proue theſe Conuerts to be of the Church, is this, their earneſt deſire to come to preſent themſelues before the Lord in his houſe. So that leaving al other marks, I dare be bold to averre out of this place; That they that come to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto God in his houſe, with true, faithful, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, penitent, and obedient ſoules, they are the true Saints and ſeruants of God. O how ſhould this moue vs to earneſt and vnfained devotion, howe ſhould this moue vs to ſing with <hi>David,</hi> O how pleaſant are thy tabernacles O Lord of hoſts! Indeede they were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and amiable to him, he could haue wiſhed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a very Potter, a dorekeeper in the houſe of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15626:17"/>God, yea when he was abſent from the Tabernacle, he lamented that his happineſſe was not ſo much as the very Sparrow, and Swallow, that ſound a neſt and building place in the Temple,<note place="margin">ſ 84.4.</note> concluding in that Pſalme, O bleſſed are they that dwel in thy houſe! I need not to tell you of the magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtructure of the Temple, how gloriouſly erected, how beautifully fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how paſt al imaginations furniſhed, how finiſhed, dedicated, bleſſed, admired, honored, freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, how eſteemed by God himſelfe as a holie manſion, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ioie of the earth, the beauty of the world, the glorie of al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the pallace of the great king, the delight &amp; paradiſe of the higheſt, where was the Arke &amp; coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt, the tables of the Teſtimonie, the Seraphins, Cherubins, and mercie ſeat, al being ſtrange things of much excellencie, but the ſummitie of al happineſſe, was the reſidence of Gods eternal fauour there. J need not to tel you of the honor that the verie heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had in their reputing of this to be moſt holy,<note place="margin">of Antiq. ib. 11.8. &amp; 2.2. &amp; 14.8.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his Antiquities teſtifieth what obſeruant regard was borne to this ſanctuarie by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, by <hi>Ptolomaens Philadelphus,</hi> by <hi>Pompey</hi> the great, and many others, J omit the ſtiles, titles, names attributs, and other encomiaſticks of this Temple.</p>
            <p>The vſe J make of the doctrine propoſed is this, to exhort euerie man to comfortable remembrance of this benefit, that he is one of Gods Church, and maie be bould to preſent himſelfe before the Lorde in his Church, that wheras manie dare not be bold to ſpeak vnto ſome others of the ſame mould and matter, dare not I ſaie, come into the preſence or enter the priuie
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15626:18"/>Chamber, yet they maie be bold to enter Gods great Chamber of preſence, the reſidence of his fauour, the habitation of his honour, his Sanctuarie, Temple, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, mountaine, houſe, Church. Ho wought this to moue vs? Seeing wee maie bee bold to come to this mountaine, yea more to the houſe of this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, nay more to the God of this houſe, of this houſe J maie wel ſaie; for if euer he were God, he was <hi>Deus Iacobi.</hi> And J from the inwards of my ſoule pray that this Court of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iames</hi> maie be as truely <hi>Domus Iacobi,</hi> as he hath bin <hi>Deus Iacobi:</hi> who knoweth not that he is <hi>Deus Iacobi,</hi> a God, a great &amp; powerful God, whoſe Court is <hi>Celum,</hi> woſe hal is <hi>expanſum,</hi> whoſe ſtarre-chamber is <hi>firmamentum,</hi> whoſe exchequer is <hi>profu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> whoſe Kings bench is <hi>Empyraeum,</hi> whoſe throne is heauen, whoſe footſtole is earth, whoſe waſhpott is the ſea, whoſe attendants be Angels, whoſe horſes be the winds, whoſe Chariots be the fire, whoſe word is his wil, whoſe wil is his command, whoſe commande is his power, whoſe power is eternal, making him fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reful to his enimies, merciful to his ſeruants, iuſt in his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, true in his promiſes, wonderful in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, meruellous in his wounders: al this is comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this he is <hi>Deus Jacobi</hi> J hope none of you are ſo ſtonie harted but wil be moued by the mountaine, or if not, by the houſe of this mountaine, or if not, by the God of this houſe, or if not, yet ſure by this title that he is <hi>Deus Jacobi,</hi> J ſhall exhort and by violence drawe ſome conuerſion, or compunction, or deuotion from you. <hi>Gratious Prince</hi> giue me leaue to ſpeake to your Highnes. J confeſſe J am not <hi>Agapetus</hi> to giue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15626:18"/>to <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> or a <hi>Plinie</hi> to giue inſtructions to <hi>Traian,</hi> or an <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to giue Councel to the young Prince <hi>Alexander:</hi> yet giue me leaue to remember your highneſſe of one higher, <hi>the Lord of Lords, &amp; the Prince of Princes,</hi> Remember his name, his feare, his ſeruice, his honour, his Church, let it for euer be your ioie, and the Crowne of your dignitie, with the good Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> rather to be <hi>membrum Eccleſiae, then caput Imperij,</hi> let the example of <hi>David</hi> be euer before your Princely eies, his <hi>profeſsion;</hi> I &amp; my houſe wil ſerue the Lord, his <hi>proteſtation,</hi> It did mee good, when they ſaid we wil goe vnto the houſe of the Lord, my feet ſhal ſtand in thy gates o Jeruſalem. So ſhall the eies that ſee you bleſſe you, &amp; the eares that heare you giue witnes to you, and the mouthes that ſpeake of you ſhal crie from the earth to the heauens, bleſſed be the wombe that bare the, and the papps that gaue thee ſuck, and God himſelfe ſhal vtter his voice from the heauen to the earth, Peace be within thy wales and plentiouſneſſe with in thy Palaces. Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſpringes of Nobilitie yee generous and in genious ſpirites, I haue not the ſpirit of <hi>Paule</hi> to ſpeake to the Noble men of <hi>Beraea,</hi> yet giue mee leaue to remember you of your duty, which the Lord requireth, Kings caſt their Crownes at his feete, and Nobles ſeeke their honour in his ſeruice. Perfourme dutie to him, and yee ſhall be more Noble then yee were borne, yee ſhal bee partakers of a new birth in Chriſt Jeſus: adde vnto the Nobilitie of your birth the Nobilitie of life, the Nobilitie of vertue is your owne, of birth your predeceſſours:</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15626:19"/>
            <q>
               <l>—Et quae non fecimus ipſi</l>
               <l>Vix ea nostra voco.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>Remember your God, his ſeruice, &amp; Religion, Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that this place is the <hi>Spring-Garden</hi> of the Nobilitie, here ye grow vp as plants, &amp; here ſhal ye be preferd to be as the poliſhed Corners of the Temple. O then remember the honor due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temple! I hope you hope for the bleſſings of the eternal life, one of them is to be made Pillars in the Temple of my God. Are you to bee pillars in the Temple of God?<note place="margin">Revel. 2,</note> O then reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the Loue you ought to ſhew vnto this temple. What ſhoulde I ſpeake of the corners or pillars of the Temple? <hi>Templum eſt is viventis Dei,</hi> yee are the Temple of the liuing God, the Scripture ſpeaketh it, I neede not demonſtrate it, your lips be the Organs of this Temple, your thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing the hymnes of this Temple, your vnity the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of this Temple, your tongues the cenſors of this Temple, your praiers the incenſe of this Temple, your hart the Altar of this Temple, your repentance the ſacrifice of this Temple, your zeale the fire of this Temple, which as the fire in the Temple, let it neuer goe out. The time wil come, when you wil acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this, &amp; condemne your ſelues for contemning this, when you wil hate the pompe, and glorie, and all the ſtate of this world, when in true iudgement you ſhal finde your gold and ſiluer to bee but the earths dregs, your ſilkes but the excrements of wormes, your Pearles but the rubble of the ſea, the ſweeteſt muſke to be natures avoidance, the moſt gorgeous apparell to bee follies garniſh and prides enſigne,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15626:19"/>the moſt faire houſes, riotts witneſſes, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions monumentes, the greateſt cheere the bodies ſtench and the bellies burthen, the greateſt offices fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours butterflies, and monies bondſlaues. Authoritie envies obiect, and cares ſubiect, &amp; the chiefeſt Glory, ſtatteries ſhaddow, and popularities apprentice. Ah las what fruit, or ioie, or comfort wil ye then haue of thoſe things whereof yee wil be aſhamed? O then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now euen now in your tender yeares, to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your ſelues to your God, for they that honor him, he wil honour them, and they that deſpiſe him, he wil deſpiſe them. Al of you, worſhipfull &amp; beloued, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what you haue hard this day, if the Text I haue choſen (the Conuerſion of the Gentiles) cannot moue you to Conuerſion, yet let the time wherein I ſpeake. It is <hi>Lent,</hi> a time of al others in the whole yeer appropriated for this holie worke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſion. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, comming to the Church, and performing of diuine offices. Jt is the time wherein Chriſt in fortie daies did ſuffer more miſery, then in all his life. It is the time in which he did hunger, faſt, thirſt, watch, praie, ſweat, bleed, faint and die for thee. That ſo he might be the Lambe of God, that taketh away the ſins of the ſinners of the world: Remember this weake, weary, bleeding, fainting, dying Lamb: worthy is this Lamb that was killed, to receiue power, and riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſtrength, and honour, and glorie, &amp; praiſe. And let al the Creatures which are in heauen, and on the earth, and vnder the earth, and in the ſea, and al that are in them, ſing praiſe, and honour, and glorie, and power, be vnto him that ſitteth vpon the throne, and vnto the Lambe for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
